[SPEAKER_00]: So, this is the Sabbāsava Sutta, Majjhima Nikāya II.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just a few sections that I want to speak about.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the first section, the basic summary of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It says, because I say that the destruction of the taints is for one who knows and sees, not for one who does not know and see.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, who knows and sees what?
[SPEAKER_00]: It says, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's translated as wise attention and unwise attention.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he knows the difference there.
[SPEAKER_01]: He knows.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, and that wise attention is yoniso manasikāra.
[SPEAKER_00]: And for now, I will translate that as an attention with perspective.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, who knows and sees what?
[SPEAKER_01]: You could probably say.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's yoniso of manasikāra, yoniso manasikāra.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you could say perspective of attention.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you know perspective of attention and non-perspective of attention.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not the attention necessarily that is different.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's when you have perspective on your attention, you don't have perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you're aware, as we say peripherally,
[SPEAKER_01]: Regarding what you're attending in front of you, or you're not aware, peripherally, regarding what you're attending in front of you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, that's exactly, that's, that's by definition, that's what perspective is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Having perspective means not being absorbed in, like, one narrow, one pointed thing, but actually having perspective on it, not losing the context of that, of that thing, of that situation.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you see why that's necessary?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because often in the suttas, we would give those similes of the trap, the poison drink, all that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And all those things can only be known if you gain perspective in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because nothing you attend in the trap will reveal the trap as a trap.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it's a trap.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you know, if you have perspective that it's a trap, then you will basically not engage with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you have perspective that it contains poison that you cannot detect, but you know
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there is perspective in regard to attending to this poisonous drink.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you will not drink it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why I said there is no single thing that would bring sensuality, engaging with your senses, to diminish as proper attention, as perspective of attention.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yoniso manasikāra.
[SPEAKER_01]: And there's not a single thing that would make sensuality to increase as not having the perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ayoniso manasikāra.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can...
[SPEAKER_00]: Being lustful towards a sensual image.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Perspective in regard to that would be, well, all the effort that you put in practicing the dhamma that then has revealed, um,
[SPEAKER_01]: The sense objects to be perilous, dangerous, resulting in death, suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not something you always have to...
[SPEAKER_01]: I have to re-attend now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, it's perilous.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not...
[SPEAKER_01]: It becomes part of the perspective, if you've been doing it rightly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, every time you attend to sensuality, as the Buddha would say, the danger is apparent.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when perspective becomes apparent, it means your yoniso, manasikāra has been properly fulfilled.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're gaining knowledge and wisdom.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have the bigger picture.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it takes effort to be focusing on the perspective, or to be discerning the perspective, while the focus is taken by sensuality, by attention here and there.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, if you invested enough of that peripheral effort, peripheral development, so to speak, then things become apparent.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, now, when I attend to sensuality, all I see is the danger.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, if I attempt to non-sensuality, all I see is peace and pleasure, pleasure of renunciation.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that takes effort to develop.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you have a perspective on what you are attracted to?
[SPEAKER_00]: True.
[SPEAKER_00]: The perspective on the nature of the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: You want to see it, those things, on the level of perspective.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not make another thing you're attending of.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because either way, you're unaware of perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how people do their subha wrongly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, I see beautiful.
[SPEAKER_01]: I must see ugly now.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that will work initially, maybe, when kind of the reality, the surreal kind of aspect of ugly hits you.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you get used to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It ceases to be surreal.
[SPEAKER_01]: Either way, you haven't developed perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's when, in the vinaya pitaka, like, all those rules that revolve around, like, basically, people being attracted to... becoming attracted to ugly, and breaking rules, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because they haven't had perspective to begin with.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you want to practice a subha rightly, it's in regard to the beautiful, you want to see the perspective as revealing the ugly underneath.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not make another thing you look at, and with your attention, and stare at.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, either way, there will be no perspective.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, if you look in the world, there's people who are attracted to even the most disgusting things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even, you know, excrement is attractive for them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, there are.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's all... because there's no perspective.
[SPEAKER_00]: So...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, no matter how... Whatever is in front of you, has potential of becoming attractive, because you haven't uprooted sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're craving for pleasure, and you're not developing perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, just have it long enough, sufficiently enough, and you'll be attracted to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you do have perspective, even the most beautiful and attractive things will actually be seen as ugly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because they are truly ugly and repulsive.
[SPEAKER_01]: If they weren't so, sensuality would not be unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sensuality would not be a contradiction.
[SPEAKER_01]: It would not be pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: It would not be a cover-up.
[SPEAKER_01]: It would not be, basically, something you you could get rid of.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when one attends with a perspective, unarisen taints arise...
[SPEAKER_00]: Without a perspective.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sorry.
[SPEAKER_00]: When one attends without a perspective, unarisen taints arise and arisen taints increase.
[SPEAKER_00]: When one attends with a perspective, or has... one has perspective on one's attention, what one is tending to, unarisen things do not arise, and arisen things are abandoned.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what you just said.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think what I was thinking of was, I think it was that, it was in Anguttara, Samādhi Sutta, but it says the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: It says the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then that's, that's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you realize it's, it's the, it's the, it's the fundamental.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, right from the start, whether you're going to be going in the right direction or the wrong direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: With perspective is the right direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Without perspective is the wrong direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you if you start without a perspective on the right level, no amount of your practice, then, can sort of change the fact that you took the first step in the wrong direction, and now that's where you're heading.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's where you've been meditating with sensuality, not free from sensuality, not really getting any distinction of the kind that matters.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, and that's why yoniso manasikāra is one of the
[SPEAKER_01]: Prerequisites for becoming a Sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's a necessary basis.
[SPEAKER_01]: If a Putrajana would have... Obviously, perspective is not a static thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Some people have more, some people have less of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Some people are wise and natural, some people are not, because they, you know, the life made them so, they made the effort, whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, fundamentally,
[SPEAKER_01]: You need more of a perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't matter how lofty, elevated, putrūjana you are or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need more perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: Perspective on the certain universal truths, universal reality of things, which is what dhamma is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that means, in other words, some people have little dust in their eyes, some people have more dust in their eyes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Either way, there is dust in their eyes that needs to be removed.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't have too much.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't have too much of the right perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Dhamma is actually uprooting all of your putrūjana's perspectives.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if they were not wrong, you would be free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: You would not need to practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's why, even as a prerequisite, yoniso manasikāra needs to be developed.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't have it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why often, like, I find it quite unfortunate, it's often translated and watered down.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, it's a wise considering.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's appropriate attention.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's all stuff that Putujana can relate to, in a sense of, oh yeah, I wisely consider and appropriately sort of approach my sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you are able
[SPEAKER_01]: To approach centrality means there is no yoniso, manasikāra in you.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the ayoniso is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ayoniso is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, basically, then, your idea of the right perspective is fully enveloped within the wrong perspective.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, actually, everyone has a perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's always some perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just whether it's going to be wrong or right, whether it's going to be limited or immeasurable, depending on... And certain direction, like a limited perspective, cannot result in immeasurable perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you were to start developing the direction of immeasurable perspective, that can result in such perspectives.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that perspective takes cultivation and development.
[SPEAKER_01]: Doesn't happen to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Cannot happen to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's something you discern on account of basically being instructed.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yoniso, manasikāra and the right instruction are the necessary two prerequisites for arising of the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you need the right instruction, but you also need to have the right perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, putujana can engage in right perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: He can start doing it, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: And with the right instruction, he'll cease to be a putujana.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, right perspective is what is described before.
[SPEAKER_01]: Looking at the universal characteristics of your current experience and not letting yourself be pulled or absorbed into the particulars of your observations, attention, techniques, sense objects and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the beginning of the... well, that's at least the direction where you will develop the right perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, obviously, the right perspective of anāgāmī, yoniso manasikāra of anāgāmī, is far superior to the possibility of yoniso manasikāra of kutujana, but it's the same direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if kutujana starts developing it, he will free himself from sensuality, for example.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's there.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the crossroads.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like left or right.
[SPEAKER_01]: So to speak, or more actually, more accurately, it's more like the two planes.
[SPEAKER_01]: One is that the horizontal plane of left, right, front and back, and yoniso manasikāra is the perpendicular plane.
[SPEAKER_01]: They would basically be surmounting any direction you take with your attention.
[SPEAKER_01]: Perspective is there unchanged.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_00]: Surmounts any... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pretty much like the nature of sati and mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is also why you can't have too much mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pretty much the same thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, let's go to the next section.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it says, it taints to be abandoned by seeing.
[SPEAKER_00]: It says here, Bhikkhu is an untaught ordinary person, a patujana, who has no regard for the noble ones, and is unskilled and undisciplined in their dhamma, who has no regard for true men and is unskilled and undisciplined in their dhamma, does not understand what things are fit for attention and what things are unfit for attention.
[SPEAKER_00]: Since that is so, he attends to things unfit for attention.
[SPEAKER_00]: He doesn't attend to things fit for attention.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he doesn't understand what things, if attended to, will obscure the perspective, and what things, if attended to, will fortify the perspective.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because he has no perspective.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's a vicious circle.
[SPEAKER_00]: He's locked in.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why he needs to start restraining beforehand, out of faith.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if he has no recognition of the value of sense restraint, and celibacy and so on, he needs to start doing it, because, see, at least, he unknowingly, he's not fueling the wrong perspective anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there is a possibility that he's going to start seeing things in the right, right context.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if he met, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: The true men, as it says, the noble ones, they were telling just that.
[SPEAKER_00]: They were telling, you don't see things correctly, but do this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Start restraining, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, that is the perilous situation of putuja, as you said many times before.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't know the escape, you don't see the truth, the right order, the right perspective, and because of that, the lack of perspective is getting worse.
[SPEAKER_00]: You think you have the right perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there has to be a perspective there, but it's just going to be wrong and more wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It says, what are things unfit for attention that he attends to?
[SPEAKER_00]: They are things such, when he attends to them, the unarisen taint of sensual desire arises, and the arisen taint of sensual desire increases.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the taint of being and the taint of ignorance.
[SPEAKER_01]: We said that in other talks.
[SPEAKER_01]: It connects the same when we spoke about the meditation and how to... how basically most people's meditation revolves around saying sīlabhātparamāsa, the virtue and duty, the fetter, the first fetter that impedes them.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's related exactly to that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So,
[SPEAKER_01]: By not knowing, by not having perspective on what you need to do, what you need to attend to, you attend to right things wrongly, wrong things rightly, wrong things wrongly, but you can't attend to right things rightly, because you have no perspective on it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, eh... and that's what happens when... when people without such perspective then, eh... take on the practice and so on, but practice is not... it's not instructing them and teaching them how to look
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, a developed perspective, in regard to what they're practicing, is just making them go through the motions of their practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, the precepts, and then do this, and then do this, and then do this, and then here is your mantra, and then do this.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the more they do it, the less, the further away from getting the direction of the right perspective they are.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have to do something.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the Buddha says what you do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sense restraint, virtue, well controlling your senses and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's what you're doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And yeah, that is a factor to begin with, even if somebody's doing it rightly.
[SPEAKER_01]: But now, you're also instructed to look at it, to gain perspective in regard to what you're doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not just do this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Do this and then understand why you're doing what you're doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can't stop doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can't stop keeping the precepts in order to understand why you're keeping the precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to keep keeping the precepts in order to be able to understand, eventually, the purpose of keeping the precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you won't be keeping them, in that sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: You won't be having to attend to them and do them, because now you understood their place and their nature and same.
[SPEAKER_01]: You wouldn't be then doing any more meditation methods and techniques, because that was done before when there was no perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: You were hoping of going through the motions, will somehow bestow the knowledge upon you.
[SPEAKER_01]: But now you realize, oh no, it's me gaining knowledge in regard to what I'm doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: In regard to keeping the precepts, in regard to sensory strain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, in regard to sitting quietly, just
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm keeping the gaze in front of myself, not being distracted.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I'm not doing it as a method or a technique that I will adhere to for 4 minutes 30 seconds.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm doing it so I can understand, like, the perspective behind.
[SPEAKER_01]: The universal characteristics of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Withdrawal, composure, mindfulness, all these things.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how understanding can arise.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how you would overcome the first factor of doing things on account of practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: And not seeing how they would be
[SPEAKER_01]: Supporting the practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Having no direct knowledge of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you just take on faith that being restrained and so on will help my practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: You take on faith that if I keep trying to meditate, I will get the right meditation.
[SPEAKER_01]: But unless your meditation, your precepts and stuff are being reflected upon and you're trying to understand them as to why is this wholesome, why is this worthy of development, why is this... why would this result in freedom from suffering, you will never understand it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because no amount of do this, do this and keep these precepts would result in dhamma arising in you.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why they said, the arahants themselves said that when they were at the first council.
[SPEAKER_01]: What should we recite first?
[SPEAKER_01]: The vinaya, the rules, or the sutta?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, the sutta is the dhamma, but then say, but there's no dhamma without vinaya.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no dhamma without the rules.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, rules are not the dhamma, but there is no dhamma without the basis of rules.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, let's recite the rules first.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, they recited all the stories from the Vinaya Pitaka and then went into dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, rules are not the dhamma, but you wouldn't be able to
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't have any dhamma whatsoever if there are no rules established.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when I say rules, I mean virtue, precepts and sense restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's all about that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like a calming fall.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like you should... you could ask yourself, as somebody who wants to practice dhamma and keep the precepts, you ask yourself, okay, so do I understand this relationship between dhamma and the precepts?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or do I think that my keeping of the precepts equates practicing of the dhamma?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it doesn't, actually.
[SPEAKER_01]: Keeping the precepts is one thing, practicing the dhamma is the other.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, oh, do I understand this?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you don't understand it, if you don't see clearly, you are taking the precepts, they are fettering you.
[SPEAKER_01]: And yeah, sīla, bhātta, paramāsa, virtue, duty, the good things, the wholesome things, are a fetter.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you have no perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ayoniso.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're attending them without perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: And even if for a hundred years...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's good in terms of making merit, being virtuous and sense-restrained, but there will be no wisdom arising.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even if for a hundred years you just keep the rules, but never invest effort into developing that perpendicular direction of... Oh, what's the... what's the context of these rules?
[SPEAKER_01]: That I will not break, but let me understand this, the purpose.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when you do, then you don't need to hold it.
[SPEAKER_01]: The knowledge has taken place.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why we say that, like, a noble person who is free from that fetter of Sīla Bhārata Paramāsa, even if they would sometimes, due to circumstances, break the rules, all they would need to do is just recognize that, and immediately, pretty much, their practice would be restored, when they see fault is fault, because they see fault is fault, they would understand it.
[SPEAKER_01]: While somebody who is not free from Sīla Bhārata Paramāsa, when they break the rules, it's even worse, because they had no perspective even with the rules.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, they can't just repair it with an insight back on, because they had no insight to begin with.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why you have to develop the direction of seeing the danger in the slightest fault, because, yeah, the slightest fault can undermine everything you build up that could have possibly helped you gain perspective on your own keeping the precepts, for example.
[SPEAKER_01]: And we spoke about it in other talks.
[SPEAKER_01]: You realize in the beginning you keep the precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you gain the perspective, it's not about me doing the precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's simply me not doing anything against the precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you don't need to keep the precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: All you need to do is not break them.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then they're there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that became your mode of behavior.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why there were no rules in the beginning.
[SPEAKER_01]: That was obvious to people who understood the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why when that monk asked the Buddha... oh, there were too many, there were a hundred-something rules at the time.
[SPEAKER_01]: He said, there's too many for me to keep.
[SPEAKER_01]: I can't wrap my head around it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he said, can you keep, what, three?
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't do anything rooted in greed, aversion and distraction.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't do anything unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: Cultivate the wholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Cultivate the wholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: So to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, even just two rules.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he wouldn't... he knew, ah, anything that I can recognize, because he had perspective, as an wholesome, I'll not do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if there is no specific letter of the rule that bans you from doing it, you know that it's bad, because it's rooted in pre-diversion delusion, and you won't do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if that's your criteria, you can never break the rules.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, yeah, you can take it even on that fundamental level.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there is no rule against, I don't know, talking to people.
[SPEAKER_00]: Something wholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you recognize that your motivation for doing so is rooted in you want to be distracted or or whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: Entertained, lustful, for whatever reason, you're engaging in that which is not unwholesome in its letter.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's unwholesome and you would have perspective on that, because your fundamental motivation is the fundamental perspective of your action.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's what we said.
[SPEAKER_01]: Every action is intention.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's rooted in your intention.
[SPEAKER_01]: That determines the action.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if, like, publicly, like, you know, from the third-person point of view, it is nothing unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're talking about books and suttas and tipiṭaka, but he does that internally for unwholesome reasons, or for not so wholesome reasons.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if your criterion now, with your right perspective, is to never do things that are rooted in greed, aversion and distraction,
[SPEAKER_01]: You can never, basically, be unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can never break the rules.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you're not guided now by the letter.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, but the rule says I can talk to people.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's like a very, eh, base criteria for people that have no criteria at all.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you should strive higher than that.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you were to develop yoniso manasikāra properly, you would have perspective that wholesome unwholesome is determined by wholesome unwholesome intention behind those actions, and that's the criteria you follow, even if there is no formulated rule against it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's... if you start practicing like that, there are no loopholes in vinaya, because it's all either rooted in wholesome or unwholesome or neutral.
[SPEAKER_01]: So yoniso manasikāra is pretty much the
[SPEAKER_01]: The fundamental thread that can take you from putujana state to being fully enlightened, if you cultivate it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I think we mentioned it before, it's like becoming that, you know, concerned for your own welfare and then recognizing the necessity of accepting responsibility for your actions, for your senses, for your intentions, for everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because when you're responsible,
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, when you feel responsible, well, you cannot afford to lose perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, this is really important.
[SPEAKER_01]: I will consider everything before I commit to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Only when you are irresponsible, you just act out.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even in mundane terms.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even in colloquial sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: Irresponsible people are people that don't really consider things.
[SPEAKER_01]: They don't really have context.
[SPEAKER_01]: They don't have perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: They just want this, don't want this.
[SPEAKER_01]: They just irresponsibly act and then pretend it never happened or whatever else.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, accepting responsibility for your own situation, even things you're not in control of, so to speak, it's it's better, because it can then prompt you in the direction of developing right perspective and right context, which is pretty much beginning of yonisumnasikāra.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, with the right instruction, you can get the right view and account of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you wonder how it would feel like to do that, well, ask yourself, even in mundane terms, is responsibility pleasant or unpleasant?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is responsibility burden?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or lighthearts are joy.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: So it's going to be heavier in the beginning, more unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because most of the life is about avoiding responsibility and getting the pleasure that covers up any sense of burden.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you realize that that's all optional, and you start accepting that burden of responsibility as a patujana, that's the basically precursor to the yoniso manasikāra.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, you know, the mundane right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, there are the results of my actions, there is, you know, there is giving, there is weight, there is significance of things.
[SPEAKER_01]: I cannot just ignore.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is the fact that I don't know.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's also the truth for you to begin with.
[SPEAKER_01]: That I'm not liberated, I'm not free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't have that wise perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So accepting the reality of your situation and responsibility for you being in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you keep yourself in whatever perspective you are in, right or wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: By cultivating wrong perspective, that's what's going to proliferate and diversify and become more.
[SPEAKER_01]: By abstaining from it and kind of going against the pull of the wrong perspective and trying to develop that perpendicular right perspective, that will be on you again.
[SPEAKER_01]: Through your own effort, you can.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, either way, you need to take responsibility.